When my son was like 1 and 1/2, he was
diagnosed with autism. And we started to
look around for services, realized our
insurance didn't cover anything, so we
went to Medicaid, and we qualified. And
my wife is spent hours and hours on the
phone with what I now know was a
corporate middleman trying to work
through these applications and
processes, and it was
mind-numbingly complicated and
difficult. And the wait times were so
long, and the paperwork and the hoops
that we had to jump through. And I
remember feeling a lot of anger at the
inefficiency of the government. The
government has no incentive to perform
because we're not their customer. What I
realize now is that I was dealing with a
corporation. I was not the customer.
Izzy was not the customer. My son Henry,
who needed services, was not the
customer. In fact, complicated forms and
more wait times and process is actually
more business for these corporate
middlemen. They have an incentive to
sell more paperwork to all of us. So,
these are the folks who are getting
government contracts to act as
government in running welfare programs.
They're basically agents of the
government. They're mercenaries for the
public sector. They're making huge
decisions that benefit the everyday
lives of low-income people.
>> To me, that is a distortion of what
Ronald Reagan dreamt about of
corporations swooping in and making our
government more efficient. Ronald Reagan
shook up the welfare system by instead
of giving money directly to people in
need, instead giving it to the states
who would then give it to a corporate
middleman who would then distribute it.
And that corporate middleman also had to
kind of determine the eligibility of
people, making sure they're working, are
they looking for a job? And all of that
is a lot of work, and these corporations
were the ones to be doing it. These
corporate middlemen were supposed to be
much more efficient in administering
this government money. And indeed, they
are for-profit companies and they
operate much more efficiently than the
government itself, cutting costs and
looking for ways to do things more
efficiently. But, let's remember, this
is not like a normal corporation like
McDonald's that is selling a product to
a customer that can go somewhere else.
Their main job is to get more government
contracts and then to cut costs so that
they can capture as much of that
government contract as profit. So, in
this case, what that means is cutting
staff, making it as cheap as possible to
process these applications. My point
here is corporate middlemen who
administer welfare are not robber barons
and they're not running some corrupt
scheme, but they are for-profit
corporations who will cut costs where
they can. And if they're not held
accountable for doing that, the people
who suffer are the people who are
already vulnerable and needy in our
country, which is what all these
programs are meant to help.